Guide to the Alen MacWeeney photographs, 1962-1986, bulk 1965 RL.11648
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Alen MacWeeney photographs
1962-1986
1965
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
RL.11648
.5 Linear Feet 1 box 14 prints
Collection comprises fourteen black-and-white inkjet prints of photographs taken in Ireland by Alen MacWeeney, chiefly in 1965. Locations include counties Donegal, Galway, Kerry, Limerick, and Sligo, and the city of Dublin. Portraits of individuals and families, as well as some of animals, coexist with depopulated, dramatic landscapes. The prints measure 13x18 inches. A photobook titled UNDER THE INFLUENCE (2011) which includes these images along with others, accompanied by excerpts of poetry by William B. Yeats, is also held by the Rubenstein Library. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
The prints all measure approximately 13x18 inches; image sizes vary and are given in the inventory. All sizes given are rounded up to the nearest 1/8 of an inch.
Biographical / Historical
Born in Dublin, Ireland in 1939, Alen MacWeeney began his career in Paris at twenty, as Richard Avedon's assistant. His work has appeared in many magazines and photography publications, and is in the permanent collections at the Museum of Modern Art, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the George Eastman House, the Philadelphia Museum of Art, the Art Institute of Chicago, and others.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Images may only be used for educational, non-commercial purposes; any other use requires the photographer's permission.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Alen MacWeeney photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2015.
Collection Overview
Collection comprises fourteen black-and-white inkjet prints of photographs taken in Ireland by Alen MacWeeney, chiefly in 1965. Locations include counties Donegal, Galway, Kerry, Limerick, and Sligo, and the city of Dublin. Portraits of individuals, including an old man in a field, a Benedictine monk, a woman in a doorway, and a farming family, coexist with depopulated, dramatic landscapes.
The black-and-white inkjet prints are printed on uncoated textured art paper, and measure 13x18 inches. Image sizes range from 6 1/8 x 10 1/4 to 11 1/2 x 10 1/4 inches.
A photobook titled UNDER THE INFLUENCE (2011) which includes these images and others, accompanied by excerpts of poetry by William B. Yeats, is also held by the Rubenstein Library.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Related Materials
Related collection: William Gedney photographs and papers, Ireland photographs, 1974, Rubenstein Library, Duke University.
Book (see Duke University Libraries catalog): Under the influence, [New York, N.Y.?]: [publisher unidentified], c2011.
Documentary photography -- Ireland; Landscapes -- Ireland; Dublin (Ireland) -- Photographs; Ireland -- Photographs; Black-and-white photographs; Digital prints; Inkjet prints; Portraits; MacWeeney, Alen; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
- Under the Influence, 1962-1986; 14 prints 1 box
  - Man at Seapoint, Dublin, 1965; Image size: 6 7/8 x 10 3/4 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11648-P-0001)
  - The Conor Pass, Kerry, 1965; Image size: 6 7/8 x 10 1/4 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11648-P-0002)
  - Farming family, Sligo, 1965; Image size: 6 7/8 x 10 1/4 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11648-P-0003)
  - Holy Well, Galway, 1965; Image size: 10 1/2 x 10 1/4 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11648-P-0004)
  - Old man in a field, Sligo, 1965; Image size: 10 1/4 x 10 1/4 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11648-P-0005)
  - Benedictine monk, Glenstal Abbey, Limerick, 1962; Image size: 10 5/8 x 10 1/4 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11648-P-0006)
  - Ruined house, Donegal, 1965; Image size: 10 1/4 x 10 1/4 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11648-P-0007)
  - Young woman, Brackenstown House, Dublin, 1965; Image size: 10 5/8 x 10 1/4 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11648-P-0008)
  - Desolate landscape, Donegal, 1965; 6 3/4 x 10 1/4 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11648-P-0009)
  - Sheep and crow, Sligo, 1965; Image size: 7 x 10 1/4 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11648-P-0010)
  - Old woman and child, Dublin, 1965; Image size: 11 1/2 x 10 1/4 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11648-P-0011)
  - Sheepdog and turf, Bloody Foreland, Donegal, 1965; Image size: 10 1/8 x 10 1/4 (Box 1, Image RL.11648-P-0012)
  - Public house snug, Dublin, 1986; Image size: 8 x 10 1/4 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11648-P-0013)
  - Policeman, man and priest, Rathmines, Dublin, 1966; Image size: 6 7/8 x 10 1/4 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11648-P-0014)